Calinescu, Matei mss., 1959-2009 LMC 2836
Lilly Library
Calinescu, Matei mss.
1959-2009
1975-2005
Lilly Library
Călinescu, Matei
LMC 2836
8 Boxes
The Calinescu, Matei mss., 1959-2009, consists of the correspondence and diaries of literary critic and Indiana University professor of comparative literature Matei Calinescu.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research. The subseries Personal II in Correspondence series, in Box 6, is closed to researchers. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Matei Calinescu, born and educated in Bucharest, Romania, was a distinguished Romanian and American literary critic and writer, publishing 14 books of literary criticism and more than 150 articles. He began his academic career in 1960 as an assistant professor at the University of Bucharest and eventually moved his career to IU Bloomington as a visiting scholar and Fullbright lecturer. He remained at Indiana University for the rest of his career until his death in 2009.
Calinescu published many well-known pieces of literary criticism, including Five Faces of Modernity: Modernism, Avant-Garde, Decadence, Kitsch, Postmodernism, (1997). He also wrote several memoirs, poetry and novels, including The Life and Opinions of Zacharias Lichter. His memoirs include Matthew's Enigma, about his relationship with his son, who was diagnosed with autism. Calinsescu also received several awards and honors: he was a Guggenheim fellow in 1975-76, a National Endowment for the Humanities fellow, and a fellow of the Woodrow Wilson Center in Washington, D.C. He received Romania's highest honor, the medal Pentru Merit by the President of Romania in 2000.
Calinescu was married to Adriana Gane (b. 1941) and had two children, Irina (b. 1965) and Matthew (b. 1977).
Arrangement
This collection has been maintained in its original order, arranged into two series: I. Correspondence and II. Diaries. This collection also includes an additional file of various Publications Lists and Book Lists.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes the correspondence and diaries of Indiana University professor of comparative literature Matei Calinescu. Calinescu's scholarly work focused on twentieth-century literature, modernity, avant-garde literature, and theories of reading and rereading. Calinescu was also interested in the literary and intellectual output from his native Romania and corresponded with various intellectuals in the Romanian diaspora.
Related Material
See Calinescu, Matei mss. II, Calinescu, Matei mss. III, Barnstone mss., Zarifopol-Johnston mss., Manea mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2014
Indiana University -- Faculty; comparative literature; Romanian Literature; immigrants; Romanians -- United States; Cold War; Parents of autistic children; Călinescu, Matei; Cioran, E. M. (Emile M.), 1911-1995; Hassan, Ihab, 1925-2015; Eliade, Mircea, 1907-1986; Ionesco, Eugène; Nemoianu, Virgil; Zarifopol-Johnston, Ilinca, 1952-2005
- Correspondence
  - General, from Calinescu to A-W, 1970-2009
    - Adamesteanu, Gabriela., 2002, March 11 - 2009, Feb. 3 (Box 1)
    - Aligica, Dragos., 1999, Jan 21 - 2009, June 5 (Box 1)
    - Anghelescu, Mircea., 1993, June 7 (Box 1)
    - Antohi, Sorin., 1996, May 9 - 2008, Aug 14 (Box 1)
    - Baciu, Stefan., 1978, July 30 - 1979, Feb 16 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Copy typed letter and mss letter with attached typed preface to Mira Simian Baciu's book of poems.
    - Balas, Egon., 2000, Mar 2 (Box 1)
    - Baltag, Alexandru., 1999, Mar 2 - 2009, May 21 (Box 1)
    - Banica, Mirel., 2009, March 25 (Box 1)
    - Banu, Georges (Bita)., 2006, June 25 (Box 1)
    - Baraboi, Otilia., 2006, Oct 23 (Box 1)
    - Bogdan, Manola., 1992, Dec 5 - 2008, Oct 3 (Box 1)
    - Borbely, Stefan., 1993, April 21 - 2006, Aug 19 (Box 1)
    - Breban, Nicolae., 1974 - 1986, Dec 31 (Box 1)
    - Calin, Vera., 1977, April 21 - 1979, July 21 (Box 1)
    - Caraion, Ion., 1982, Sept 16 (Box 1)
    - Cesereanu, Ruxandra and Corin Braga., 2002, Dec 16 - 2007, Nov 28 (Box 1)
    - Chivu, Marius., 2007, Aug 3 & Sept 18 (Box 1)
    - Cioran, Emil., 1988, April 18 (Box 1)
    - Ciurea, Doina., 1994, May 16 (Box 1)
    - Codrescu, Andrei., 1984, Jan 18 - 2006, Dec 19 (Box 1)
    - Coeckelsbergs, René., 1978, Mar 28 - July 21 (Box 1)
    - Colin, Amy., 1979, Jan 2 - 1986, April 10 (Box 1)
    - Comorovski, Neli., 1978, Mar 26 & July 2 (Box 1)
    - Compagnon, Antoine., 1991, April 11 (Box 1)
    - Constantin, Ilie., 1974, Feb 21 (Box 1)
    - Cornis-Pope, Marcel., 1986, Mar 11 - 1989, Jan 30 (Box 1)
    - Craiutu, Aurelian (Relu)., 1998, Oct 20 - 2009, Mar 31 (Box 1)
    - Cristea-Enache, Daniel., 2006, Feb 24 - 2009, Feb 5 (Box 1)
    - Cugno, Marco., 2007, Sept 8 (Box 1)
    - Culianu, Ioan Petru., 1987, Nov 21 (Box 1)
    - Deciu-Ritivoi, Andreea., 2006, Mar 24 - 2007, Feb 12 (Box 1)
    - Dobrescu, Caius., 2002, Mar 27 (Box 1)
    - Doinas, St. Aug. (Stiva)., 1999 (Box 1)
    - Duna, Raluca., 2004, Jan 12 - 2009, May 31 (Box 1)
    - Duna, Teodor., 2006, Dec 22 - 2008, Mar 3 (Box 1)
    - Eliade, Mircea., 1973, Jan 19 - 1982, Mar 11 (Box 1)
      Copies mss and typed letters archived in the University of Chicago Library, one draft, one copy of letter; various
    - Federman, Raymond., 1979, Mar 29 - 1981, Oct 15 (Box 1)
    - Finkenthal, Michael., 1999, Oct 11 - 2009, March 10 (Box 1)
    - Gelehrter, Lucian (Lou)., 1997, Jan 8 - 2006, June 6 (Box 1)
    - Georgescu, Vlad, Georgescu, Mary and Georgescu Tudor., 1979, June 25 - 2008, March 13 (Box 1)
    - Goma, Paul., 1979, May 28 - 1994, April 14 & May 8 (Box 1)
    - Graff, Gerald., 1977, April 25 & Nov 21 (Box 1)
    - Gregori, Ilina., 1998, Mar 6 - 2009, May 7 (Box 1)
    - Hassan, Ihab., 1978, Mar 1 - 1991, Aug 30 (Box 1)
    - Heim, Michael., 1999, May 23 - 2000, Mar 30 (Box 1)
    - Hollander, Paul., 1982, June 3 (Box 1)
    - Illias, Christina., 1999, Jan 19 - 2009, April 4 (Box 1)
    - Indiana University., 1978-2009 (Box 1)
    - Ionesco, Eugene., 1980 (Box 1)
    - Ionescu, Gelu., 1977, Dec 18 - 2009, May 30 (Box 1)
    - Ivanovici, Victor., 1989, June 12 - 2009, April 24 (Box 1)
    - Johnston, Kenneth., 2005, Oct 16? - 2009, April 20 (Box 1)
    - LaCapra, Dominick., 1982, Mar 31 (Box 1)
    - Lerner, Veronica., 2006-2007 (Box 1)
    - Levin, Harry., 1982, Sept 16 (Box 1)
    - Liiceanu, Gabriel., 2002, Aug 5 (Box 1)
    - Lovinescu, Monica and Virgil Ierunca., 1994, July 25 (Box 1)
    - Mamali, Catalin., 1995, July 9 (Box 1)
    - Manea, Norman., 1993, Feb 10 - 2009, June 8 (Box 1)
    - Marcu, Luminita., 2002, Mar 30 & April 2 (Box 1)
    - Marcus, Solomon., 1996, Sept 27 - 2008, Dec 24 (Box 1)
    - Marino, Adrian., 1982, June 4 - 2001, Dec 22 (Box 1)
    - Martin, Mircea and Angela., 1990, July 10 - 2008, Dec 16 (Box 1)
    - McPherson, William., [1995, May] - 2000, Feb 6 (Box 1)
    - Melinescu, Gabriela., 1979, June 3 & 1992, Oct 30 (Box 1)
    - Moraru, Christian., 1993, April 13 - 2009 (Box 1)
    - Musat, Carmen., 2002, Oct 28 - 2007, June 21 (Box 1)
    - Nasta, Mihai and Riri., 1988, Jan 19 & 1989, Nov 28 (Box 1)
    - Negoitescu, Ion., 1980, Mar 27 - 1999, Mar 20 (Box 1)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil., 1976, Mar 16 - 1979, Dec 31 (Box 1)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil., 1980, Feb 1 - 1986, Aug 5 (Box 1)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil., 1987, May 10 - 1997, Dec 27 (Box 1)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil., 1988, Jan 3 - 1999, Dec 18 (Box 1)
    - Oisteanu, Andrei., 2006, Jan 10 - 2009, Jan 29 (Box 1)
    - Palanciuc, Luiza., 2006, Oct 5 - 2008, March 2 (Box 1)
    - Paruit, Alain., 2005, Mar 28 - April 25 (Box 1)
    - Pavel, Toma., 1977, Nov 25 - 2008, Dec 24 (Box 1)
    - Perloff, Marjorie., 1982, May 21 - 2009, Feb 25 (Box 1)
    - Petrescu, Dan., 2002, April 20 - 2006, Dec 1 (Box 1)
    - Petreu, Marta., 2000, May 30 - 2009, June 20 (Box 1)
    - Plesu, Andrei., 2002, Mar 6 (Box 1)
    - Raicu, Lucian (Bernard)., 1992, Oct 21 & 1993, Jan 23 (Box 1)
    - Ralescu, Anca and Dan., 1999, April 23 - 2000, May 29 (Box 1)
    - Rawson, Claude., 1990, May 29 (Box 1)
    - Reszler, André., 1977, Dec 2 - 1993, Jul 9 (Box 1)
    - Roman, Andrei., 1994, Dec 16 (Box 1)
    - Sora, Simona., 2007, Feb 25 - 2009, Feb 3 (Box 1)
    - Sorkin, Adam., 2008, April 3 - 2009, Feb 21 (Box 1)
    - Sparisou, Mihai., 1979, Nov 14 & 30 (Box 1)
    - Spiridon, Monica., 1990, July 10 - 2002, March 6 (Box 1)
    - Stanescu, Gabriel., 2002, Mar 19-20 (Box 1)
    - Stolojan, Sanda., 1996, July 1 (Box 1)
    - Tanase, Stelian., 1995, July 12 - 1997, Feb 24 (Box 1)
    - Tepeneag, Dumitru., 1970, Oct 11 - 1992, Jan 17 (Box 1)
    - Tiron, Corina., 2004, Jan 27 - June 18 (Box 1)
    - Tismaneanu, Vladimir., 1995, Aug 9 - 2007, Feb 14 (Box 1)
    - Turodan, Dorin., 1992, Nov 10 - 1993, Apr 22 (Box 1)
    - Various (English)., 1976-2006 (Box 1)
    - Various (Romanian)., 1978-2009 (Box 1)
    - Various, Students., 1980-2007 (Box 1)
    - Verona, Roxana., 2004, Jan 23 - 2009, May 29 (Box 1)
    - Vianu, Lidia., 1993, May 2 - 1999, Oct 14 (Box 1)
    - Visniec, Matei., 2005, Oct 19 - Nov 10 (Box 1)
    - Voinescu, Sever., 2004, Feb 2 - 2006, Oct 10 (Box 1)
    - Volovici, Leon., 2001, July 8 (Box 1)
    - Wellek, René and Nonna., 1974, Aug 25 - 2000, Feb 20 (Box 1)
    - Zarifopol-Johnston, Ilinca., 2000, Feb 29 & Mar 3 (Box 1)
  - General, A-I to Calinescu, 1963-2009
    - Adamesteanu, Gabriela., 1990, Oct 17 - 2003, Aug 20 (Box 2)
    - Alexandrescu, Sorin and Liliana., 1978, Oct 15 - 2003, Aug 20 (Box 2)
    - Alexandru, Ion., 1969, Nov 23 & 1970, Apr 29 (Box 2)
    - Aligica, Dragos., 1999, Apr 10 - 2009, June 2 (Box 2)
    - Anghelescu, Mircea., 1993, May 10 - 2009, June 2 (Box 2)
    - Antohi, Sorin and Mona., 1995, Oct 12 - 2009, June 18 (Box 2)
    - Baciu, Stefan and Mira Simian., 1974, Jan 3 - 1979, Mar 16 (Box 2)
    - Balas, Egon., 2000, Feb 11 & Apr 9 (Box 2)
    - Baltag, Alexandru., 1997, May 10 - 2009, May 12 (Box 2)
    - Baltag, Cezar., 1973, Mar 12 - 1995, Jan 9 (Box 2)
    - Banica, Mirel., 2001, Jul 27 - 2009, Apr 5 (Box 2)
    - Banu, Georges (Bita)., 2002, Nov. 26 (Box 2)
    - Baraboi, Otilia., 2006, Mar 29 - 2009, Apr 20 (Box 2)
    - Barnstone, Willis., 1975 - 1985, Mar 19 (Box 2)
    - Berindei, Mihnea. n.d. (Box 2)
    - Bernard, Noel., 1974, Sep 9 - 1977, July 5 (Box 2)
    - Berza, Luri., 1978, Feb 12 - 1991 (Box 2)
    - Blandiana, Ana., 1974, Jan 2 - 2002, Mar. (Box 2)
    - Bogza, Geo., 1969, Nov 17 & 1970, Jan 9 (Box 2)
    - Borbely, Stefan., 1992, Jan 25 - 2008, Mar 8 (Box 2)
    - Breban, Nicolae., 1965 - 2003, Jan 15 (Box 2)
    - Brezianu, Andrei., 1985, July 7 - 2003, Dec 6 (Box 2)
    - Calin, Vera., 1976, Oct 5 - 1980, July 20 (Box 2)
    - Caraion, Ion., 1982, Jan 10 - 1983, Apr 16 (Box 2)
    - Carlson, C. Thomas., 1984, Sep 12 - 1985, May 30 (Box 2)
    - Cartarescu, Mircea., 1991, Jan - 2007, Aug 27 (Box 2)
    - Cassian, Nina., 1985 - 1990 (Box 2)
    - Celan, Paul., 1968, Mar 14 (Box 2)
    - Cesereanu, Ruxandra., 1995, Apr 14 - 2009, Jun 23 (Box 2)
    - Chihaia, Pavel., 1989, Aug 17 - 1994, Oct 6 (Box 2)
    - Cioran, M. Emil., 1972, Jul 2 - 1988, May 7 (Box 2)
    - Ciuli, Sorin., 1984, Feb 9 (Box 2)
    - Ciurea, Doina., 1974, Dec 27 - 1994, Dec 6 (Box 2)
    - Codrescu, Andrei., 1987, Aug 15 - 1998, Oct 5 (Box 2)
    - Coeckelberghs, René., 1978, Mar 21 - 1979, May 29 (Box 2)
    - Colin, Amy., 1978, Dec 17 - 2005, Oct 6 (Box 2)
    - Comorovski, Cornelia., 1977, Dec 27 - 1986, Nov 1 (Box 2)
    - Compagnon, Antoine., 1991, Apr 12 (Box 2)
    - Cordos, Sanda., 2002, Mar 11 - 2005, Dec. (Box 2)
    - Cornis-Pop, Marcel., 1984, Dec 15 - 1995, May 21 (Box 2)
    - Craiutu, Aurelian., 1995, Oct 16 - 2007, Nov 15 (Box 2)
    - Cristea, Dan., 1986, Mar 19 (Box 2)
    - Cugno, Marco., 2007, June 21 - 2008, Mar 7 (Box 2)
    - Culianu, Ioan Petru., 1973, Oct 28 - 1989, Dec 22 (Box 2)
    - Cunningham, Rodger., 1989, Nov 27 - 1990, Jan 22 (Box 2)
    - Deciu-Ritivoi, Andreea., 2007, Jan 10 & Mar. (Box 2)
    - Deligiorgis, Stavros and Ioanna., 1975, Nov 26 - 1983, Mar 2 (Box 2)
    - Dobrescu, Caius., 1990, Feb 20 - 2002, Apr 17 (Box 2)
    - Doinas, Stefan Augustin (Stiva)., 1973, Feb 12 - 2002, May 27 (Box 2)
    - Doniger, Wendy., 1987, Nov 7 - 2007, Sep 26 (Box 2)
    - Dorian, Marguerite., 1974, Sep 23 - 1995, Nov 4 (Box 2)
    - Duna, Raluca., 2003, June 17 - 2009, June 15 (Box 2)
    - Duna, Teodor., 2007, Feb 15 - 2008, Jan 11 (Box 2)
    - Eliade, Mircea., 1973, Feb 13 - 1982, Apr 30 (Box 2)
    - Federman, Reymond., 1979, Mar 20 - 1981, Oct 22 (Box 2)
    - Feldman, Burton., 1976, Feb 17 - 1978, Jan 8 (Box 2)
    - Finkenthal, Michael., 1998, Oct 19 - 2009, Jun 18 (Box 2)
    - Foias, Ciprian., 1980, Oct 10 - 1990, June 26 (Box 2)
    - Fokkema, Dowe., 1990, Aug 15 - 1993, Apr 20 (Box 2)
    - George, Al. (Georgescu, George)., 2002, Dec 5 & 2003, Feb 1 (Box 2)
    - Georgescu, Tudor., 2006, Mar 7 - 2009, Jan 21 (Box 2)
    - Georgescu, Vlad and Mary., 1973, Jan 30 - 1995, Mar 15 (Box 2)
    - Gelehrter, Lou., 1996, Jan 13 - 2009, May 21 (Box 2)
    - Gihl, M. Eliza., 1981, Mar 6 - 1991, Jan 23 (Box 2)
    - Golopentia, Sanda., 1980, Sep 23 - 2001, Sep 4 (Box 2)
    - Goma, Paul., 1994, Mar 26 (Box 2)
    - Graff, Gerald., 1977, Apr 19 - Nov 27 (Box 2)
    - Gray-McDonald, Margot., 1989, Feb 9 - Dec 6 (Box 2)
    - Gregori, Ilina., 1982, Feb 26 - 2009, Apr 19 (Box 2)
    - Guran, Letitia., 1995, Jun 1 - 1998, Mar 17 (Box 2)
    - Hassan, Ihab & Sally., 1978, Feb 24 - 1991, Aug 16 (Box 2)
    - Hassing, Richard., 1974, Feb 24 - 1977, Jun 21 (Box 2)
    - Heim, Michael., 1999, May 20 - 2007, Sep 24 (Box 2)
    - Hollander, Paul., 1982, May 21 (Box 2)
    - Holquist, Michael., 1986, Sept. 22 (Box 2)
    - Horasangian, Bedros., 2002, July 22 & 2003, Aug 28 (Box 2)
    - Ierunca, Virgil., 1974, Jun 14 - 1986, Apr 23 (Box 2)
    - Ilea, Daniel., 2004, May 30 & 2004, July 19 (Box 2)
    - Illias (Ilioaia), Christina., 1988, Nov 6 - 2006, Sep 28 (Box 2)
    - Impey, Michael., 1974, Feb 19 - 1981, Apr 24 (Box 2)
    - Indiana University., 1974-2007 (Box 2)
    - Indiana University, Dept. of Comparative Literature., 1978-2007 (Box 2)
    - Ionesco, Eugène. letter of rec., 1969, Aug. 12 & 1976, Feb 17 (Box 2)
    - Ionescu, Gelu. (Folder 1 of 2), 1963, Dec 3 - 1982, June 11 (Box 2)
    - Ionescu, Gelu. (Folder 2 of 2), 1982, Dec 16 - 2009, May 30 (Box 2)
    - Iosifescu, Silvian., 1974, July 20 & 1974, Aug 5 (Box 2)
    - Ivanovici, Victor., 1989, Apr 11 - 2008, May 17 (Box 2)
  - General, I-P to Calinescu, 1968-2009
    - Johnston, Elisabeta (Betty)., 1974, Nov 25 & 1974, Nov 29 (Box 3)
    - LaCapra, Dominick., 1982, Apr 11 - 1982, Oct 26 (Box 3)
    - Lefter, Bogdan., 1991, Dec 21 - 1993, Dec 7 (Box 3)
    - Lerner, Veronica., 2006, Jun 6 - 2007, Mar 14 (Box 3)
    - Levin, Harry., 1973, Nov 26 - 1974, Dec 12 (Box 3)
    - Liiceanu, Gabriel., 2002, Aug 1 (Box 3)
    - Livezeanu, Irina., 1989, Sep 15 - 1998, Jan 14 (Box 3)
    - Lovinescu, Monica., 1994, July 14 (Box 3)
    - Mamali, Catalin., 1995, May 22 & 1996, Dec 20 (Box 3)
    - Manea, Norman., 1988, Nov 14 - 2009, June 15 (Box 3)
    - Manolescu, Florin., 2002, Jan 14 - 2002, Aug. (Box 3)
    - Manolescu, Nicolae., 1982, Apr 22 (Box 3)
    - Marcu, Luminita., 2002, Apr 4 - 2002, July 14 (Box 3)
    - Marghescu, Mircea., 1975, Jan 4 - 1981, Oct 15 (Box 3)
    - Marcus, Solomon., 1992, Jan 29 - 2009, May 3 (Box 3)
    - Marino, Adrian. (Folder 1 of 6), 1964, Oct 6 - 1969, Nov 5 (Box 3)
    - Marino, Adrian. (Folder 2 of 6), 1970, Sep 9 - 1983, Oct 21 (Box 3)
    - Marino, Adrian. (Folder 3 of 6), 1990, Mar 11 - 1991, Dec 9 (Box 3)
    - Marino, Adrian. (Folder 4 of 6), 1992, Jan 10 - 1993, Nov 2 (Box 3)
    - Marino, Adrian. (Folder 5 of 6), 1994, Jan 2 - 1996, Nov 5 (Box 3)
    - Marino, Adrian. (Folder 6 of 6), 1998, Mar 18 - 2003, Feb 20 (Box 3)
    - Martin, Mircea., 1969, Oct 22 - 2008, Aug 13 (Box 3)
    - McPherson, William., 1995, Aug 28 - 1997, Mar 2 (Box 3)
    - Melinescu, Gabriela., 1976, Aug 25 - 2006, Dec 13 (Box 3)
    - Mihailescu, Calin-Andrei., 1987, July 8 - 1992, Jan 23 (Box 3)
    - Moraru, Christian., 1990, June 19 - 2003, Dec 25 (Box 3)
    - Moss, Stanley., 1990, June 20 (Box 3)
    - Mungiu-Pippidi, Alina., 1999, Dec 18 (Box 3)
    - Musat, Carmen., 2005, Feb 10 (Box 3)
    - Nasta, Domnica., 1985, Jan 28 - 1988, Jan 1 (Box 3)
    - Nasta, Mihai & Riri., 1983, May 30 - 2003, Aug 14 (Box 3)
    - Negoitescu, Ion. plus Testament, 1968, June 10 - 1992, Oct 12; 1993 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 1 of 8), 1973, Mar 4 - 1976, Nov 22 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 2 of 8), 1977, Jan 18 - 1979, Dec 27 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 3 of 8), 1980, Jan 25 - 1983, Dec 24 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 4 of 8), 1984, Jan 19 - 1986, Dec 25 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 5 of 8), 1987, Mar 4 - 1992, Jul 24 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 6 of 8), 1997, Jan 8 - Dec 28 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 7 of 8), 1998, Jan 3 - 1998, Dec 25 (Box 3)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil.(Folder 8 of 8), 1999, Jan 4 - 1999, Dec 14 (Box 3)
    - Nicolae, Cosana., 1992, Jan 13 - 1993, May 13 (Box 3)
    - Niculescu, Mihai., 1985, Dec 10 - 1986, Jan 11 (Box 3)
    - Nivat, Georges., 1982, Sept 28 (Box 3)
    - Ocneanu-Thiery, Ionana., 2002, Nov 11 - 2005, Apr 5 (Box 3)
    - Oisteanu, Andrei., 2002, Aug 11 & 2008, June 12 (Box 3)
    - Orlich, Ileana., 2005. Sept 6 & Dec. (Box 3)
    - Palanciuc, Luisa., 2006, Dec 21 - 2008, Aug 21 (Box 3)
    - Parry, Barbara., 1989, Dec 24 - 1993, Jan 6 (Box 3)
    - Paruit, Alain., 2005, Mar 25 & 2005, Aug 2 (Box 3)
    - Patapievici, H-R., 1996, June 25 & 2003, Dec 4 (Box 3)
    - Paun, Gheorghe (Dr)., 1993, Jan 24 & 1993, May 6 (Box 3)
    - Pavel, Laura., 1998, Jan 5 - 2000, Nov 17 (Box 3)
    - Pavel, Toma.(Folder 1 of 2), 1970, Feb 15 - 1978, Feb 23 (Box 3)
    - Pavel, Toma.(Folder 2 of 2), 1979, Jan 4 - 2005, Jan 6 (Box 3)
    - Perahim, Marina Vanci., 2008, Dec 1 (Box 3)
    - Perloff, Marjorie., 1981, Nov 26 - 2009, Jan 10 (Box 3)
    - Perry, Thomas A., 1974, Mar 1 - 1998, Jan 6 (Box 3)
    - Petrescu, Dan., 2002, Apr 5 - 2006, Dec 2 (Box 3)
    - Petreu, Marta., 1991, Sep 16 - 2009, June 13 (Box 3)
    - Pillat, Dinu., 1972, Mar 18 & 1972, July 7 (Box 3)
    - Plate, Liedeke., 1996, Dec 14 - 2011 (Box 3)
    - Plesu, Andrei., 2002, Mar 8 - 2002, Apr 22 (Box 3)
    - Pop, Mihai (Misco)., 1990, Dec - 1993, Mar 9 (Box 3)
    - Popescu, Petru., 1974, Jan 28 - 1975, June 3 (Box 3)
  - General, R-W to Calinescu, 1963-2009
    - Raicu, Lucian & Sonia Larian., 1990, June 11 - 2007, July 31 (Box 4)
    - Ralescu, Anca & Dan., 1984, July 25 - 1999, Apr 27 (Box 4)
    - Raitu, Ion., 1986, April 2 (Box 4)
    - Reszler, André., 1973, July 19 - 2002, Aug 22 (Box 4)
    - Roman, Andrei., 1989, Feb 26 - 1995, Jan 16 (Box 4)
    - Roznoveanu, Mirela., 1990, Apr 4 - 1992, Jul 27 (Box 4)
    - Russell, Charles., 1981, Sept 16 - 1983, Nov 4 (Box 4)
    - Simion, Eugen., 1974, Mar 4 - 1991, June 17 (Box 4)
    - Sinyavski, Andrei., 1981, Aug. 25 (Box 4)
    - Solacolu, Ion., 2002, June 17 & July 15 (Box 4)
    - Solt, Mary-Ellen & Solt, Susan., 1985, Mar 26 - 1989, Apr 25 (Box 4)
    - Sora, Mariana., 1982, Apr 16 & 1989, Mar 22 (Box 4)
    - Sora, Simona., 2007, Mar 6 - 2008, May 21 (Box 4)
    - Sorkin, Adam J., 2002, Oct 29 & May 19 (Box 4)
    - Spariosu, Mihai., 1975, Feb 28 - 2002, Oct 14 (Box 4)
    - Spiridon, Monica., 1984, June 11 - 2004, Jan 11 (Box 4)
    - Spulber, Nicolas., 1989, Sept 4 & Oct 9 (Box 4)
    - Stanescu, Nichita., 1963, June 20 - 1968, June 15 (Box 4)
    - Steinhardt, Nicolae (Nicu)., 1971, April 17 - 1972, Sept 22; 1968, Aug 5) (Box 4)
      Includes letter from Archimandrite Justinian Chira, Rohia, 1968, Aug 5).
    - Stoenescu, Stefan., 1984, Mar 9 - 1999, Dec. (Box 4)
    - Stolojan, Sanda., 1975, July 11 - 2002, Apr 29 (Box 4)
    - Stroe, Aurel., 1973, April 10 (Box 4)
    - Tanase, Stelian., 1995, July 12 - 1998, Aug 14 (Box 4)
    - Teodorescu, Magda., 1991, Nov 10 - 2003, July 15 (Box 4)
    - Tepeneag, Dumitru (Tepe). (Folder 1 of 2), 1968, May 4 - 1975, Sept 5 (Box 4)
    - Tepeneag, Dumitru (Tepe). (Folder 2 of 2), 1977, Oct 28 - 2009, Jan 10 (Box 4)
    - Theim, Barbara & Jon., 1980, Nov 11 - 2005, Sept 25 (Box 4)
    - Tiron, Corina., 2004, Jan 23 - June 21 (Box 4)
    - Tismaneanu, Vladmir (Volo)., 1989, May 10 - 2007, Feb 2 (Box 4)
    - Toiu, Constantin., 1978, Sept 20 & Oct 24 (Box 4)
    - Tudoran, Dorin., 1985, Aug 23 - 1992, Nov 15 (Box 4)
    - Ursache, Mihai., 1982, Jan 9 - June 25 (Box 4)
    - Various (English)., 1974, Mar 24 - 2008, May 22 (Box 4)
    - Various (Romanian)., 1974, Nov 6 - 2009, May 7 (Box 4)
    - Various, Students (English)., 1980, Jan 9 - 2009, May 8 (Box 4)
    - Verzea, Ileana., 1982, June 13 - 1983, Nov 17 (Box 4)
    - Vianu, Lidia., 1991, Nov 20 - 1998, Dec 27 (Box 4)
    - Voinescu, Sever., 2002, Feb 6 - 2003, June 19 (Box 4)
    - Volovici, Leon., 1997, Jan 26 - 2006, Dec 31 (Box 4)
    - Wellek, René & Nonna., 1974, Sept 13 - 2000, Mar 2 (Box 4)
    - Writers' Union of Romania., 2006, Mar 20 - 2007, June 7 (Box 4)
    - Zarifopol-Johnston, Ilinca., 1985, Nov 22 - 2003, July 19 (Box 4)
    - Zeani, Virginia., 2008, Dec 28 (Box 4)
    - Zlotescu, Ioana (Joy)., 2006, Nov 7 & 8 (Box 4)
  - General, Topics, A-W, 1977-2009
    - A.R.A., 1991, Apr 23 - 1991, May 3 (Box 4)
    - Autism, 2003, July 7 - 2004, June 28 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei.Five Faces of Modernity., 1978, Jan 16 & 1990, Apr 12 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei. Interviews., 2001, Oct 21 - 2002 Apr 4 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei.The Life and Opinions of Zacharias Lichter., 1974, July 18 - 2009, Feb 9 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei.Mateiu I. Caragiale., 2008, Jan 17 - 2008, Sept 15 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei.Matthew's Enigma., 2003, Dec 19 - 2010, Apr 18 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei.Portretul lui M., 2003, Oct 30 - 2009, Mar 4 (Box 4)
    - Calinescu, Matei.Rereading., 1989, Dec 26 - 1990, June 22 (Box 4)
    - Celan, Paul., 1988, May 10 - 2004, Feb 25 (Box 4)
    - Cioran, E.M., 1983, May 15 - 2008, July 28 (Box 4)
    - Culianu, Ioan P., 1992, Mar 6 - 2002, Nov 14 (Box 4)
    - Eliade Mircea. (Folder 1 of 2), 1979, July 10 - 2000, Feb 18 (Box 4)
    - Eliade Mircea. (Folder 2 of 2), 2001, Apr 5 - 2009, Mar 17 (Box 4)
    - Goma, Paul and Vianu, Ion., 1977, Apr 16 (Box 4)
    - Ionesco, Eugène., 1995, Aug 9 - 2007, Feb 6 (Box 4)
    - Ivanescu, Mircea., 1984, June 2 - 2009, Feb 21 (Box 4)
    - Romania (op-ed articles, declarations, open letters)., 1989-1999 (Box 4)
    - Romanian Studies at IU., 1991, Feb 22 (Box 4)
    - Sebastian, Mihail., 1988, Jan 15 - 2008, Apr 14 (Box 4)
    - Solt, Mary Ellen., 2007, June 26 - 2007, Oct 4 (Box 4)
    - Wellek, René., 1990, Mar 12 (Box 4)
      Copy Letter of Matei Calinescu and Virgil Nemoianu, Appeal to Czech Ambassador.
  - Personal, Friends and Family, 1959-2009
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 1961, May 26 - 1962, Dec 6 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 1963, Jan 2 - 1972, Nov 21 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 1975, July 28 - 1980, May 13 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 1986, May 28 - 1999 Dec 4 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 2001, Mar 31 - 2007, May 27 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Dora., 1977, Jan 10 - 1980, Oct 13 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Irena., 1999, Jan 24 - 2009, May 6 (Box 5)
    - Ghestin, Claudia (Soso)., 1995, Aug 22 - 2009, June 16 (Box 5)
    - Pascot, Marina (Ina)., 1978, Apr 27 - 2009, June 18 (Box 5)
    - Various., 1993, May 27 - 2009, Apr 9 (Box 5)
    - Mircea, Andrei., 1980, June 24 - 2000, Mar 13 (Box 5)
    - Various., 2004, Feb 25 - 2009, June 2 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 1964 - 1968, Apr 13 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Adriana (Uca)., 1975 - 2009, June 15 (Box 5)
    - Calinescu, Dora., 1974, May 5 - 1983, Sept 20 (Box 5)